Guide to the Frances Hesselbein Papers, 1942-2013 AIS.2013.16
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Frances Hesselbein Papers
1942-2014
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hesselbein, Frances
AIS.2013.16
51.07 Linear Feet (38 Record Center boxes, 5.5 Hollinger boxes, 1 flat box, 1 tube, and 3 media boxes)
Frances Hesselbein (1915-2022) was a figure in the world of leadership and nonprofit management, having served as the National Executive Director of the Girl Scouts of the United States of America for nearly fifteen years. She was the Chair of The Frances Hesselbein Leadership Forum at the University of Pittsburgh's Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA), Johnson Institute for Responsible Leadership, and served as the President and CEO for the organization's previous iterations. The collection consists of business materials from her organization, such as meeting minutes and conference planning information, as well as the different publications produced by the Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit Management, the Leader to Leader Institute, and the Frances Hesselbein Leadership Institute. The personal materials in the collection include event information, correspondence, as well as materials dealing with the Girl Scouts of the United States of America. There are paper records, as well as video cassettes, audio tapes, photographic images, and CD-ROMs included in the collection.
Scope and Content Notes
The Frances Hesselbein Papers document the life and work of one of the leaders in the world of nonprofit management. The collection contains a wide variety of materials, including information on the Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit Management (1990-2002), the Leader to Leader Institute (2003-2011), and the Frances Hesselbein Leadership Institute (2012-2017), as well as Hesselbein's personal life. The records are divided into two subgroups, the records of the Hesselbein Institute and its predecessors; and the personal records of Frances Hesselbein. Materials are dated as early as the 1930s and 1940s, up until the present day. Most of the material comes from the time towards the end of Hesselbein's tenure with the Girl Scouts of the United States of America in the 1980s and continues through her work with The Drucker Foundation/Leader to Leader/Hesselbein Institute.
The records in these subgroups represent two distinct categories of information, as specified by the donor. In the first subgroup, that of the institution, there are materials relating to Hesselbein, but there are also materials more specifically concerned with the Institute itself, such as meeting minutes, conference plans, publications, staff correspondence, and audio/visual materials produced by or relating to the institution. There are also records of Peter Drucker himself, such as articles written over his lifetime and information related to the Drucker Institute at Claremont Graduate University in Claremont, California, where Drucker was a professor.
In the second subgroup, containing personal material, there are records related to Hesselbein's time with the Girl Scouts, information on other nonprofit organizations with which she spent time, copies of speeches given in the past 35 years, and audio/visual materials relating to these topics, as well as Hesselbein herself. There is also information on events attended by Hesselbein, and documents relating to her family life as well. The materials in this subgroup, unlike in the first, almost always deal specifically with Frances Hesselbein.
Biography
Frances Richards Hesselbein (1915-2022) was born in Johnstown, Pennsylvania, in 1915, the oldest of three children. Her education includes classes at the University of Pittsburgh's Johnstown Campus, though after her father died she left school and supported her family. She married John D. Hesselbein, an alumnus of the University of Pittsburgh, who worked for the Johnstown Tribune-Democrat and later opened his own documentary-filmmaking and photography studio. While assisting her husband at the studio and raising their son, John, Hesselbein was approached by a local group of women with the request to take over the leadership of a local Girl Scout troop. Despite not having a girl in the troop herself, Hesselbein agreed and took charge since the troop would be disbanded without a leader. She stayed with that group of girls until they graduated high school. Later, she was asked to take on the role of Talus Rock Council Executive Director in Johnstown, which she accepted. Following a successful period in this position, she was invited to apply for the position of National Executive Director (CEO) of the Girl Scouts of the United States of America. She served in that role from 1976-1990 as the first woman to be appointed to that position from within the organization.
During her time with the Girl Scouts, Hesselbein helped to transform the organization. She had the uniform redesigned as well as the logo, worked to increase minority representation, and also helped create the Daisy program for 6-year-old girls. Membership in the Girl Scouts increased greatly under Hesselbein's leadership as well, reaching up to 2.25 million girls in all. Hesselbein also implemented her leadership strategy of "Banning the Hierarchy", incorporating the idea of "Circular Management." This strategy, among others, would follow Hesselbein when she retired from the Girl Scouts.
After leaving the Girl Scouts in 1990, Hesselbein was invited to work on a new project. Her friend Peter Drucker, often called "The Father of Modern Management" for his business expertise, was to be honored by a new nonprofit organization dedicated to promoting leadership and management skills and tools, which would eventually be called the Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit Management. Hesselbein led the organization through the 1990s in different roles. In 2003, the organization was renamed the Leader to Leader Institute though the mission of the institute remained the same. In 2012, it would become the Frances Hesselbein Leadership Institute, which Hesselbein led as President and CEO. In 2017, Hesselbein partnered with the University of Pittsburgh, who acquired the organization, which was renamed The Frances Hesselbein Leadership Forum. The Hesselbein Forum resides in the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA), Johnson Institute for Responsible Leadership.
Hesselbein served as the Chair of the Hesselbein Forum, as well as the editor-in-chief of the Leader to Leader Journal.
Hesselbein was very active in various nonprofit organizations in addition to her work at the Hesselbein Forum. She worked with retired members of the military to promote the Generals in Transition and the Investment in America programs. She has served on the boards of nonprofits and corporations, including the Bright China Social Fund and Mutual of America Life Insurance Company. In 2009, working with her alma mater, Hesselbein helped establish the Frances Hesselbein Global Academy for Student Leadership and Civic Engagement at the University of Pittsburgh, inviting students around the world to participate in sessions focused on creating the leaders of tomorrow.
Frances Hesselbein received a number of awards, including 22 honorary degrees. In 1998 she was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom by President Bill Clinton, as "a pioneer for women, diversity, and opportunity." She also served as the West Point Class of 1951 Chair for the Study of Leadership, a two-year appointment. Hesselbein was the first woman and the first non-graduate to hold this position. Hesselbein was also named a Distinguished Daughter of Pennsylvania.
Frances Hesselbein died on December 11, 2022 at her home in Easton, Pennsylvania at the age of 107 years.
Access Restrictions
Researcher access to Subgroup A., Series VII. Hesselbein Fellows is subject to the Archives & Special Collections confidentiality agreement.
Previous Citation
Frances Hesselbein Papers, 1942-2014, AIS.2013.16, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Nonprofit organizations -- United States -- Management; Presidential Medal of Freedom; Johnstown (Cambria County, Pa.); Conferences; Records and correspondence; Leadership in girls; Hesselbein, Frances; Girl Scouts of the United States of America; Frances Hesselbein Leadership Institute; Leader to Leader Institute; Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit Management; Drucker, Peter F. (Peter Ferdinand); Schubert, Richard F.; Collins, James; Bennis, Warren G.; Johnston, Rob; Mutual of America Life Insurance Company; University of Pittsburgh; Buford, Bob; New York (N.Y.)
- Frances Hesselbein Institute Papers, 1942-2014; A.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Frances Hesselbein Institute Papers are a subgroup of the overall collection. Records in this subgroup come from the Drucker Foundation (1990-2002), which was later renamed the Leader to Leader Institute (2003-2011), and then again later renamed the Frances Hesselbein Leadership Institute (2012-2017); all this occurred while the organization maintained its focus on leadership, management, and the nonprofit sector. Included in this subgroup are administrative materials from these organizations, as well as records of Peter Drucker himself. There are press articles on the institutions and any associated entities, as well as publications both from the organizations and about them. Any media for the Hesselbein Institute and its related organizations is featured in Series VIII of this subgroup. The materials in this subgroup are mainly dated from the late 1980s to the early 2000s, though there are some exceptions from both earlier and later times.
  - The Peter F. Drucker Foundation, 1990-2003; I.
    This series contains the board meeting materials, management reports, correspondence between board members, notes from Frances Hesselbein, information on the Foundation's name change to the Leader to Leader Institute (including legal documents), financial information, and records relating to the Drucker Foundation's Annual Conference and Innovation Award. The materials are dated from 1990-2003, when the Foundation underwent a name change. Researchers should refer to Series VIII of this subgroup for The Drucker Foundation's A/V materials.
    - Administrative Material, 1990-2002; 1.
      - Drucker Foundation Development meeting materials, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Board of Directors Task Group meeting, May 17, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Advisory Board meeting, November 26, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Advisory Board meeting, November 27, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Board of Governors Policies and Procedures, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Board of Governors meeting, June 18, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 24, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Board of Governors meeting, April 15, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Board of Governors meeting, June 17, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Board of Governors meeting, November 12, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Board of Governors meeting, January 23, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 22, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Plan of Work, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Board of Governors meeting, January 18, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Planning meeting, March 30, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Planning meeting, May 17, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Board of Governors meeting, November 7, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Board of Governors meeting, January 17, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Drucker Foundation meeting with Richard Schubert, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Board of Governors meeting, April 11, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Board of Governors meeting - conference call, May 11, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 21, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Board of Governors meeting - conference call, March 14, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 20, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Board of Governors retreat and meeting, February 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Board of Governors meeting, May 12, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 31, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Board of Governors meeting, March 26, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 31, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Board of Governors meeting, January 13, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Board of Governors meeting, February 11, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Board of Governors meeting, May 12, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Board of Directors mailings, June 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Board of Governors meeting, September 14, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Management team meeting, September 28, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Board of Governors meeting, January 14, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Drucker Foundation Self-assessment, January 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Board of Governors meeting, May 18, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Board of Governors meeting, September 14, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Board of Governors meeting, February 14, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Board of Governors meeting, May 15, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Board of Governors meeting, September 18, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Board of Governors meeting, February 11, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Board of Governors meeting, May 7, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Board of Governors meeting, September 9, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Board of Governors meeting, February 10, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Board of Governors meeting, May 6, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Board of Governors meeting, September 22, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Board of Governors meeting, October 23, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Board of Governors meeting, November 4, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Drucker Foundation Board meeting Summaries of Action and Minutes, 1990-2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Drucker Foundation Leadership transition, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Drucker Foundation Advisory Board information, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Management team meeting materials, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Peter F. Drucker Foundation - Vision, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Board meeting planning/logistics, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Frances Hesselbein Board meeting notes, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Drucker Foundation poster, 1990s (Box 2, Tube 1)
    - Legal Information, 1991-1999; 2.
      - Drucker Foundation By-laws, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - The Leadership Network partnership information, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Drucker Innovation Award media content contracts, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Nonprofit Tax Exemption files, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
      - Fake Peter Drucker materials, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Discovery Site Media Release, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1990-2002; 3.
      - Board of Governors correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Drucker Foundation potential name change correspondence, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Board of Governors correspondence, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Board of Governors correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Financials, 1990-2001; 4.
      - Audits and financial statements, 1990-2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Balance sheets and financial statements, 1991-1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Drucker Foundation fundraising initiative, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Drucker Foundation fundraising history, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Kellogg Foundation Grant, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Drucker Conference materials, 1991-2002; 5.
      - Drucker Innovation Award Log, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Drucker Innovation Award video transcripts, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Drucker Foundation Innovation Award endowment investment policies, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Drucker Innovation Award survey results, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans - spring, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans - fall, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference materials - fall, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, October 22, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Drucker Innovation Award, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference materials - spring, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans - fall, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 22, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
      - Drucker Innovation Award, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans and materials, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 27, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Drucker Innovation Award, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Drucker Foundation/Aspen Institute conference plans and materials, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference materials - fall, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Conference video information, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Drucker Innovation Award brochure, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Drucker Innovation Award volunteer application readers, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 12, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Drucker Innovation Award - distribution and promotion, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Drucker Innovation Award dinner materials, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Drucker Innovation Award winner video, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Drucker Innovation Award winner announcements, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans and materials, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference assorted materials, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 11, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Drucker Innovation Award, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Drucker Foundation/Kauffman Foundation Conference materials, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference materials - fall, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 16, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Drucker Innovation Award, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Drucker Innovation Award video documents, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Emerging Partnerships Conference materials, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference closing speech, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 15, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Multi-Tiered Mentoring Initiative, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Salmon Corps, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Physicians Reach Out, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - The Computer Clubhouse, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Drucker Innovation Award, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans and materials, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference script, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference video transcripts, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, September 9, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Drucker Innovation Award dinner, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Times Square Jobs Training Corps, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Ocean Bank Center, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Organization of the Future Conference materials, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference materials, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Drucker Foundation Conference - Getty Event speech, November 7, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Opening Plenary, November 8, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Hesselbein Fellows Luncheon script, November 8, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Opening Plenary, November 9, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Innovation Award dinner script, November 9, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Closing Plenary, November 9, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Drucker Foundation partner dinner, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Workshop speech notes, November 1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference tape transcripts, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, August 24, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - California Transportation Training Institute, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Congregate Restaurant Meals for Seniors, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Drucker Innovation Award application - Volunteer Tax and Loan Program, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Conference Board video transcript, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Organization of the Future Conference materials, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Organization of the Future Conference speech, February 17, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Drucker Foundation pre-conference workshop speech, October 29, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans and materials, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Opening Plenary, October 30, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference moderator/speaker speeches, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Awards dinner script, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - final session speech, October 31, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - tape transcripts, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Opening Plenary, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Collaboration Challenge Luncheon speech, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Plenary Sessions, November 13, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Board of Governors dinner speech, November 11, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Hesselbein Fellows Breakfast speech, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference - Team Training meeting speech, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - Drucker Innovation Award Selection Committee meeting, August 15, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
      - Organization of the Future Conference - opening session, February 22, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - Drucker Foundation Annual Conference plans and materials, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - Drucker Innovation Award dinner, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      - Drucker Foundation Conference staff notes, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Projects and Programs, 1991-2002; 6.
      - Self-Assessment Tool presentation, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Teleconference series plans, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 35-36)
      - Self-Assessment Tool draft, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Self-Assessment Tool marketing plan, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 38-39)
      - Civic Television Network proposal, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Seminar by Satellite description and budget, April 1995 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Teleconference script, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Board Committee descriptions, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 43)